Finding Aid for Information Technology Division (University of Michigan) records, 1956-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Central Files 1984-1997
  - 1984-1992
    - Topical File
      - Grants (by ITD)
        - Marks, Greg (misc. notes addressing a variety of topics) 1984-1985 (Box 5)
        - MEET: STUDENTS, "Bad Jokes" Item 1987 (Box 5)
        - Michigan Media Computer Repair Service Reorganization 1987 (Box 5)
        - MTS (Michigan Terminal System) 1985-1987 (Box 5)
        - Networking, 1985-1987) (Box 5)
          (memos, reports, etc., re: proposals for campus computer networks)
        - Personnel 1986-1987 (Box 5)
        - Policy Statements circa 1987-1991
          (includes "Conditions of Use," "Proper Use of Information Resources," "Information Technology, and Networks," and "Guidelines for Interaction with Corporate Representatives")
          - FOIA (Freedom of Information Act) (Box 5)
        - Reorganization (ITD) 1989, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Research Resources 1985 (Box 5)
        - Rescomp (Residence Hall Computing) Program 1985-1988 (Box 5)
        - Software Licensing 1985-1987 (Box 5)
        - Space Needs 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Statistics Lab 1984-1987 (Box 5)
        - Student Computer Forum 1985 (Box 5)
        - Supercomputers 1984-1988 (Box 5)
        - UNIX 1985-1987 (Box 5)
        - Van Houweling, Douglas E.
          - Biographical Information/Resumes (Box 5)
          - Interview Transcript May 1989 (Box 5)
          - Articles/Speeches, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - News clippings 1984-1990, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - 1984-1997
    The Central Files (6.5 linear ft., 1984-1997) are divided into five subseries: Budget Material, ITD Committees, University-wide and Beyond Committees, Correspondence, and Topical Files.
    - Budget Material
      The Budget Material includes planning documents, projections, and working papers for 1988 to 1996; the amount of material varies from year to year. The records document ITD’s efforts to maintain financial stability while grappling with rapid technological change and periodic reorganization.
      - 1988-1990 (Box 23)
        - General, 2 folders (Box 23)
        - Projections 1990-1994 (Box 23)
        - Resource Administration 1990 (Box 23)
      - 1990-1991, 3 folders
        - General (Box 23)
        - Budget Request (Box 23)
        - Planning (Box 23)
      - 1991-1993, 6 folders (Box 23)
        (includes 2 folders for 1991 retreat)
      - 1993-1994, 3 folders (Box 24)
      - Sources and Uses 1994-1996 (Box 24)
    - Committees (ITD)
      There are two subseries dealing with committees: ITD Committees and University-wide and Beyond Committees. These subseries consist of enhanced documentation for several internal initiatives, such as total quality management. Documentation is continued for important university-wide technology oriented committees. Records of the Information Technology General Council (ITGC), an 80-member body created in 1988, provide documentation on the exchange of concerns and suggestions generated from a broad membership representing all units on campus. The records of the Information Technology Policy Committee (ITPC), a ten-member advisory panel, are a source for gaining an overview on issues requiring analysis, strategic direction, and policy recommendation The records of the Information Technology Architecture Committee (ITAC), formed in 1987 as a standing committee of ITPC, document the coordination of UM’s evolving integrated computing environment. Since ITPC, ITGC, and ITD senior managers report to the Executive Computing Committee (ECC), the ECC files are the best resource for garnering information on priority setting, resource allocation and final strategic direction for the development of University of Michigan information technology. Committee files typically include minutes, agendas, correspondence and often include important background information on issues under discussion. Additional material related to these major committees is held in the Deputy Vice Provost for Information Technology series of this record group (Gregory Marks served as the initial chair of ITAC), and in the Computing Center record group. The records in the Committees subseries also include files generated by Van Houweling’s service on several committees organized by President Duderstadt.
      - All ITD Staff 1995 (Box 24)
      - IBM / UM Executive Steering Committee 1991 (Box 24)
      - Operations Lead Team 1993-1995, 7 folders (Box 24)
      - Projects Planning Committee 1986-1987 (Box 24)
      - Quality Council 1995, 2 folders (Box 24)
      - Quality Improvement Team 1993 (Box 24)
      - Senior Management Committee 1991-1993, 5 folders (Box 25)
      - Strategic Lead Team 1992-1993 (Box 25)
      - Supervisory Group 1992 (Box 25)
      - Total Quality Management Team 1992-1993 (Box 25)
    - Committees (University-Wide and Beyond)
      - Administrative Technology Working Group 1992-1993 (Box 25)
      - Brainstorm Initiative Group 1997 (Box 25)
      - Commission on Preservation and Access 1990-1991 (Box 25)
      - Computing Policy Committee 1987-1989 (Box 25)
      - Consortium for Research on Telecom Policy and Strategy 1995 (Box 25)
      - Digital Libraries (3-D Initiative),1995 (Box 25)
      - Executive Computing Committee (ECC) 1992-1995, 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Futures (UM) 1991-1992 (Box 25)
      - Information Services Division Policy Committee (ISD Policy) 1993 (Box 25)
      - Information Technology Architecture Committee (ITAC) (2 expandable folders) 1986-1988 (Box 26)
      - Information Technology General Council (ITGC) 1989-1991 (Box 26)
      - Information Technology Policy Committee (ITPC) 1987-1996, 2 folders; 6 folders (Box 26)
      - Michigan Mandate Retreat 1992 (Box 26)
      - National Advisory Committee 1995 (Box 26)
      - PEW Campus Roundtable 1994 (Box 26)
      - President's Advisory Group 1991-1992 (Box 26)
      - President's Council 1990-1996, 2 folders (Box 26)
        (includes Subcommittee on Telecommunication and Information Systems)
      - President's Discussion Group 1994 (Box 26)
      - Process Management Executive Committee 1995 (Box 26)
      - Provost's Administrative Group 1993 (Box 26)
      - Strategic Planning Committee 1990 (Box 26)
      - University Committee on Information Technology (UCIT) 1992-1996 (Box 27)
      - XI Faculty Group 1995 (Box 27)
    - Correspondence
      The correspondence subseries is slight and is comprised partly of traditional correspondence, as well as printouts of electronic mail. There is also a file of e-mail printouts in the Topical Files subseries, reflecting the early use ITD staff made of the technology for internal and external communication. The Topical Files subseries, arranged alphabetically, reflects ITD’s involvement in community generated activities, national initiatives, internal and external projects, and long-range planning. Van Houweling’s participation in the deliberation of policy at the national level is evident in files including the Council on Competitiveness, Vision 2010, the Democratic Issues Group, the National Information Infrastructure and the U.S. Department of Commerce. Speeches files hold transcripts of several of Van Houweling Washington, D.C. testimonials. Also of significance are several folders documenting the phasing out of MTS (Michigan Terminal System) and ITD’s efforts to manage controversy during the transition to distributed computing. Included is a 1994 document entitled, “Moving from an MTS Centered Computing Environment to Distributed Computing Environment,” which was designed to clarify issues and answer questions. Other files of significance include records documenting reorganizations in 1990/1991 and 1994/1995. Changes in 1991 involved major cuts and reallocations in an era of cost restraints; 1995 brought dramatic restructuring and significant downsizing with a movement toward highly service focused technical staffing. The series also contains several reports, including “Priority Services Review: Perceived Value Study Report,” 1991 and “Special Task Force on Statistical Support at the University of Michigan,” 1989.
      - 1990-1997 (Box 27)
        (includes e-mail printouts)
      - Regents 1995 (Box 27)
      - Van Houweling, Personal 1993-1994 (Box 27)
    - Topical
      - Ann Arbor Schools 1994 (Box 27)
      - Annenberg CPB (Corporation for Public Networking) Project (Box 27)
      - Berkeley Review 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 27)
      - Carnegie Melon 1996 (Box 27)
      - Collaboration for Research on Electronic Work 1995 (Box 27)
      - Colorado School of Mines 1992 (Box 27)
      - Conferences
        - Networks for Networkers II 1991 (Box 27)
        - Vision 2010, 1995 (Box 27)
      - Council on Competitiveness 1995 (Box 27)
      - Democratic Issues Group 1995 (Box 27)
      - Detroit Free Press 1995 (Box 27)
      - Digital Libraries 1993-1995 (Box 27)
      - Distance Learning 1995 (Box 27)
      - Diversity 1989 (Box 27)
      - Drop Ship 1995 (Box 27)
      - E-Mail Migration Project 1993 (Box 27)
      - E-Mail Printouts 1994 (Box 27)
      - Economic Dinner Group 1995 (Box 27)
      - Encryption 1997 (Box 27)
      - Executive Officer's Retreat 1996 (Box 27)
      - Executive Search 1995 (Box 27)
      - Fungibility 1993 (Box 27)
      - Future Computing Environment Projects 1993 (Box 27)
      - Geographical Information System (GIS) 1995 (Box 27)
      - Gopher 1992 (Box 27)
      - Heinrich Hertz Institute 1997 (Box 27)
      - House of Representatives 1995 (Box 27)
      - ISODE Consortium 1991 (Box 27)
      - JSTOR (Electronic Access to Scholarly Literature) 1994-1995 (Box 27)
      - Kellogg Foundation 1995 (Box 27)
      - Legal
        - Grievance Report 1991, 1 folders (Box 52)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2021 ]
        - Intellectual Property Issues 1994 (Box 27)
      - LINKS Conference 1996 (Box 27)
      - Lotus Notes 1994 (Box 27)
      - Marketing Research 1996 (Box 27)
      - MTC (Midwestern Technology Coop) 1995 (Box 27)
      - MTS (Michigan Terminal System)
        - General 1989-1992, 2 folders (Box 27)
        - Phase Out 1994 (Box 27)
      - Michigan Information Technology Network (MITN) 1992 (Box 27)
      - National Information Display Lab 1996 (Box 27)
      - National Information Infrastructure 1992 (Box 27)
      - New Media 1995 (Box 27)
      - Northwestern Review 1995 (Box 28)
      - Organizational Charts 1995-1998 (Box 28)
      - Orientation 1995 (Box 28)
      - Outreach 1995 (Box 28)
      - Penn State Visit 1994 (Box 28)
      - People Soft 1996 (Box 28)
      - Perceptions in the Work Environment 1994 (Box 28)
      - Personnel 1989-1991 (Box 28)
      - Phi Gamma Delta 1995 (Box 28)
      - Planning
        - 1984-1986 (Box 28)
        - 1990-1995 (Box 28)
      - Policy 1992 (Box 28)
      - Project Tracking 1995 (Box 28)
      - Purchasing 1993 (Box 28)
      - Reorganization 1989-1990 (Box 28)
      - Reorganization 1995, 5 folders (Box 28)
      - Reports
        - Internal General 1990-1992 (Box 28)
        - "Ethical and Psychological Issues in Virtual Reality," 1997 (Box 28)
        - "Next Step in Customer Satisfaction," 1996 (Box 28)
        - "Priority Services Review, Perceived Value, Study Report," 1991 (Box 28)
        - "Research Computing Task Force Interim Report," 1994 (Box 28)
        - "Scientific Computation," 1993 (Box 28)
        - "Special Task Force on Statistical Support at the University of Michigan," 1989 (Box 28)
      - Residential Computing undated (Box 28)
      - Sector Study 1995 (Box 28)
      - Space 1995 (Box 28)
      - Speeches 1989-1994 (Box 29)
      - Strategic Data Planning (Executive Computing Committee) 1995 (Box 29)
      - Surveys 1992 (Box 29)
      - Team Leader Training 1993 (Box 29)
      - Technology Partners 1994 (Box 29)
      - Tillinghast, Richard 1995 (Box 29)
      - Time-Warner Conference 1994-1995 (Box 29)
      - UMTV 1995 (Box 29)
      - US Dept. of Commerce 1995 (Box 29)
      - User Relations ("Confer Problems") 1987, 3 folders (Box 29)
      - User Services 1995 (Box 29)
      - Virtual Reality 1994-1997 (Box 29)
      - White, George Congressman Visit 1992 (Box 29)
      - Womack, Ferris 1994 (Box 29)
      - X.500 1991-1993, 4 folders (Box 29)
      - Zanzibar Group 1997 (Box 29)
      - Zorea, Carlos 1996 (Box 29)
- Divisions 1976-1995
  The Division series is divided into three subseries: 1976-1992, 1986-1995, and 1964-1994, reflecting separate accessions. The series contains records from ITD's many different administrative divisions, including the Center for Information Technology Integration, and the Computing Center. Records contain information on the activities and projects of each division, as well as information on their core functions and structure.
  - 1976-1992
    The 1976-1992 subseries (3 linear ft.) includes records of the administrative units of ITD from Van Houweling's office files, including the Center for Information Technology Integration (CITI), Computing Center, Consulting Support Services, Instructional Technology Systems, Network Systems, Office of Administrative Systems, Research Systems, Resource Administration, and University Information Systems. CITI files hold correspondence and reports on various projects, most notably the development of the Institutional File System (IFS). Records for the Computing Center (some pre-dating the establishment of ITD) document its management and planning through advisory and planning reports. Also of interest is the Computer Use Allocations file, a tally of computing funds distributed to various units on campus. Office of Administration Systems records includes general correspondence and a chronological run of correspondence from the office of division director Sam Plice. Research Systems material also contains documentation on the development of IFS and a 1992 report to ITD staff on the future of MTS.
    - Center for Information Technology Integration (CITI) (Box 6)
      - General 1986-1988, 1992, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - IFS (Institutional File System) Project
        - Status Reports 1991, 1992 (Box 6)
    - Computing Center
      - General 1984-1989, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Reports, 2 folders
        - "Advisory Task Force on Computing Access Report" 1984 (Box 6)
        - "Strategic Directions and Initiatives, 1984-1987" September 15, 1984 (Box 6)
        - "Computing Center: Organization, System Architecture and Hardware Facilities" April 1985 (Box 6)
        - "Progress Report: Microcomputer Education Center" April 1987 (Box 6)
        - "Central Systems Support Group Long Range Project Plan" January 1989 (Box 6)
        - "Review Committee Report" 1986 (Box 6)
      - Computer Use Allocations
        - General 1979-1987, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Cumulative Allocations 1981-1984 (Box 6)
      - Public Workstation Clusters 1985-1986 (Box 6)
    - Consulting and Support Services (CSR) 1989-1992
      - Marketing for Information Technology (Box 7)
        (includes material for Ann Arbor Observer article)
      - Planning Team 1990-1991 (Box 7)
      - "Statement of Direction" Committee 1992 (Box 7)
    - Instructional Technology Systems 1989-1992 (Box 7)
    - Network Systems 1991-1992 (Box 7)
    - Office of Administrative Systems 1984-1988
      - Admissions Systems Project 1984 (Box 7)
      - Budget Proposal 1987/88 (Box 7)
      - Campus Network 1988 (Box 7)
      - Data Systems Center 1984-1987 (Box 7)
      - Information Systems Services 1985-1987 (Box 7)
      - Telecommunications Systems
        - General 1984-1986 (Box 7)
        - Progress Reports 1984-1985 (Box 7)
        - Status Reports 1984-1986 (Box 7)
        - Networking 1987-1988 (Box 7)
      - Telephone Systems (UMTel) 1986-1987
        - Correspondence (Sam Plice Files) (Box 7)
        - 1976-August 1977, 5 files (Box 7)
        - September 1977-1986, 27 files (Box 8)
        - 1989-1990 (Box 8)
    - Research Systems
      - IFS (Institutional File System)
        - 1990-1992, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - MTS (Michigan Terminal System), 199 (Box 9)
        (Future of MTS)
    - Resource Administration
      - Budget 1991-1992 (Box 9)
      - Diversity/Personnel (Box 9)
    - University Information Systems (UIS)
      - General 1990-1991, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Executive Information System Pilot Project 1990-1991 (Box 9)
      - Status Reports August 1991-July 1992 (Box 9)
      - System Access Requirements (Flow charts) (Box 9)
  - 1986-1995
    The Divisions, 1986-1995 subseries (2 linear ft.) is most substantive for CITI (Center for the Information Technology Integration), primarily with documentation for the development of IFS. The $40 million prototype system, known at inception internally as “Strawman,” was collaboration with IBM orchestrated by Van Houweling and directed by Gregory Marks. The records provide detailed technical documentation for the development of the software that allowed data to be shared among different computer operating systems without users having to engage in explicit file transfer procedures. The files also include a 1990 history of the project, media announcements, meeting minutes, correspondence, notes and planning documents. The evolution of the project is evident in “Summary of the IFS Project,” 1988; “IFS: An Overview,” 1988; and in a folder entitled “Contract Negotiations,” 1988. Some additional documentation on the IFS project is held in the Computing Center record group. Less extensive, but interesting, material exists for other ITD units: Network Systems, Research Systems, User Services, University Information Systems, and Instructional Technology Systems. Of particular interest in the Research Systems file is a report to the director (Bert Herzog) raising issues, concerns, and offering recommendations during a 1990 reorganization planning period. The folder also contains notes for a dialogue with Van Houweling two years later, after significant downsizing and a lack of clarity on the future of MTS led to uneasiness among staff. Instructional Technology Systems files document the management of campus computing sites, sales and services for instructional computing. Network Systems files offer some illustration of the work of the unit in coordinating several campus and national networking initiatives, including MichNet, UMnet and UMTel, the Telecommunication Systems Office.
    - Center for Information Technology Integration (CITI)
      - General,1986-1995 (Box 30)
      - Strawman (Institutional File System / IFS)
        - Central Server Structure 1988 (Box 30)
        - "Functional Characteristics of an Institutional File System," 1988 (Box 30)
      - Hardware Review Meeting 1988
        - History 1990 (Box 30)
        - IFS Contract Negotiations 1988 (Box 30)
        - IFS: An Overview 1988 (Box 30)
        - "Institutional File System Criteria," undated (Box 30)
        - Media Announcements 1988 (Box 30)
        - Meetings, Correspondence and Notes 1987-1988, 9 folders (Box 30)
        - "Michigan Implementation Plan," 1988 (Box 30)
        - "Official University Documents," 1988 (Box 30)
        - "Protocol Structure for Institutional File System Messages," undated (Box 30)
        - Straw Man Architecture undated (Box 30)
        - "Summary of the IFS Project," 1988 (Box 30)
        - Systems (Articles on file systems), 1 folders (Box 30)
        - General and Miscellaneous 1988-1992, 1 folders (Box 30)
    - Instructional Technology Systems (ITS) 1993 (Box 31)
    - Network Systems (NS) 1992-1993, 2 folders (Box 31)
    - Office of Instructional Technology (OIT) 1989-1992 (Box 31)
    - Operations Lead Team 1988-1995 (Box 31)
    - Research Systems (RS) 1990-1992 (Box 31)
      (1 expandable folder)
    - University Information Systems (UIS) 1982-1995, 3 folders (Box 31)
    - User Services (US)
      (includes Data Systems)
      - 1987 (Box 31)
        includes Data Systems
      - 1992-1993 (Box 31)
  - 1984-1994
    The 1984-1994 subseries (4 linear ft.) is comprised of administrative files created within the Computing Center division. There is, however, material created by other ITD divisions and projects. The earliest material in the series is a cluster of documentation relating to MicroGroup. This group, formed at the request of Aaron Finerman, Director, Computer Center, in 1983. The formation of the group was a response to IBM’s announcement of the “personal computer.” By 1987, increased demand for personal computers dispersed this group into the overall ITD organization structure.
    - Announcement of File Transfer Protocol Support (FTP) 1989 (Box 62)
      [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2024 ]
    - Apple Computer Lease Agreement 1994 (Box 62)
    - AppleLink License Agreement 1987-1988 (Box 62)
    - Budget Materials
      - 1986-1987 (Box 62)
      - 1989 (Box 62)
      - 1991 (Budget and Priorities Group) (Box 62)
      - Unfunded Projects 1990 (Box 62)
      - Working Group 1994 (Box 62)
    - C2S3 (Campus Commuting Sites, Sales, and Service) Merger with Campus SS 1993 (Box 62)
    - CAEN (Computer Aided Engineering Network) 1988 (Box 62)
    - Campus Computing Sites Inventory
      - 1986-1988 (Box 62)
      - 1991 (Box 62)
    - Campus Fiber Network 1988-1989 (Box 62)
    - Center for Information Technology Integration (CITI) 1986 (Box 62)
    - Classification Task Force 1991 (Box 62)
    - Computer Rentals 1992 (Box 62)
    - Computer Sites, Problems 1993 (Box 62)
    - Computer Sales Marketing Plan 1990-1992 (Box 62)
    - Computing Center
      - CONFER: CC: STAFF 1989 (Box 62)
      - Director’s Discussion 1987-1989 (Box 62)
      - Director Search Committee Memo March 1986 (Box 62)
      - Documentation 1989 (Box 62)
      - Management Training 1987-1988 (Box 62)
      - Rates: Current Considerations December 9, 1988 (Box 62)
      - Review 1986 (Box 62)
      - Survey 1988 (Box 62)
      - User Services Planning Team Report
        - October 9, 1986 (Box 62)
        - October 22, 1986 (Box 62)
    - Computing Policy Committee Minutes 1987 (Box 62)
    - Computing Resources on Campus September 1986 (Box 62)
    - Computing Survey
      - Graduate Students April 1993 (Box 62)
      - Undergraduate Student Orientation September 1992 (Box 62)
    - CONFER: CC:STAFF x9790 to be taken out of the Unyn?, June 1989 (Box 62)
    - CONFER: USER FORUM Public workstation clusters: How much or little space is enough? April 8, 1985 (Box 62)
    - Consulting Task Force Report July 15, 1986 (Box 62)
    - Cultural Audit Results December 10, 1993 (Box 62)
    - Data Resource Management and Policy Need September 1992 (Box 62)
    - Data Systems Center Rate Analysis 1991-1992 (Box 62)
    - Disk Recovery and User Services 1988 (Box 62)
    - Distributed Computing Discussion 1992-1993 (Box 62)
    - Educom
      - Ann Arbor Conference: Lessons from the Past, Strategies for the Future 1989 (Box 62)
      - InfoNet Project 1989 (Box 62)
    - Computing Policy Committee Minutes 1987 (Box 63)
    - Elsevier, “Tulip” (The University Licensing Information Program) Progress Report 1992 (Box 63)
    - Electronic Mail
      - E-Mail/Conferencing Migration Proposal, Three-year plan June 1992 (Box 63)
      - Policy 1992-1994 (Box 63)
    - Executive Committee, Internet Backbone Port Allocation 1991 (Box 63)
    - Faculty Task Force on Instructional Technology, preliminary faculty interview results May 26, 1993 (Box 63)
    - Fungibility Report 1993 (Box 63)
    - Future Computing Environment (FCE) Committee 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box 63)
    - Guidelines
      - For Compliance with New Federal Requirement on Indirect Cost Calculations, December 11, 1992 (Box 63)
      - For Interaction with Corporate Representatives, 1989-1990 (Box 63)
      - For Placing Sign-on Messages on UM-MTS and UB-MTS, 1988 (Box 63)